Guide to the George and Mary Schlosser Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
George and Mary Schlosser Papers
1901-1988
RG 19
Yale University Divinity School Library
5
(13 boxes)
The papers document the work of the conservative Free Methodist Church in central China. Both George and Mary Schlosser was active in evangelistic work in the countryside and came in close contact with the Chinese people. Famine relief work, societal routine, and the disruption of Chinese society during the period 1908 to 1949 are documented. George and Mary Ogren Schlosser were missionaries under the Free Methodist Church Foreign Missionary Board. Stationed primarily in Honan Province, George served from 1908 until his death in 1936. Mary served from 1909 to 1936, and then returned to China from 1939 to 1940 and 1946 to 1949. In the years between her missionary work she was a pastor in North Dakota and South Dakota.
Schlosser, George, 1875-1936
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Frances Schlosser Scherer.
Biographical / Historical
1875 George Donald Schlosser born in Clinton County, Missouri, son of John and Drusilla Schlosser
1885 Maria Christina (Mary) Ogren born in Jamestown, New York, daughter of J. Peter and Anna Maria Ogren
1896-1898 GDS attended South Dakota Agricultural College.
1898-1899 GDS joined First South Dakota Infantry of U.S. Volunteers and saw action in the Philippines.
1905 Jan GDS entered Greenville College, a Free Methodist college in Greenville, Illinois.
1905 Sep MCO entered Greenville College, joined Student Volunteer Band, met GDS who was Band's leader.
1906 Nov GDS left Greenville to serve in South Africa under the Foreign Missionary Board of the Free Methodist Church.
1907 GDS and MCO engaged
1907 fall GDS received permission to switch his field from Africa to China, his first choice and MCO's strong preference.
1908 Mar GDS arrived in China, took responsibility for an orphanage in Tsing Kiang P'u, Kiangsu Province. Orphanage was financed by Christian Herald magazine.
1909 MCO graduated from Greenville College.
1909 Dec-1911 Jan MCO stationed in Chengchow for language study.
1911 Jan 13 GDS and MCO married. Children: Frances, Mary Winifred, John, Anabel. Frances later served as a nurse for Yale-in-China.
1911 Civil war forced evacuation of missionaries to Shanghai; GDS returned to Tsing Kiang P'u for famine relief work.
1914-1918 Schlossers stationed in Kaifeng and Kihsien, Honan Province; Mary was active in evangelistic work among women while George had administrative as well as evangelistic duties.
1918-1919 Furlough in U.S.
1919-1927 Stationed in Kihsien, summers spent in Chikungshan
1927-1928 Furlough in U.S.
1928-1936 Stationed in Kihsien for one year, then in Jungtseh, Honan Province
1936 Dec 9 GDS died in St. Louis, Missouri, while family was on furlough.
1939-1940 MOS in China for one year before disruption of war caused her return to U.S.
1942-1944 MOS served as pastor of Free Methodist Church in Valley City, North Dakota.
1946-1949 MOS returned to China, stationed first in Kaifeng and then in Chungking.
1951-1952 MOS served as pastor of church in Brookings, South Dakota.
1955 Apr 18 MOS died in Kansas.
For additional biographical information see: George and Mary Schlosser: Ambassadors for Christ in China by Frances Schlosser Scherer
Scope and Contents
The Schlosser Papers are a valuable addition to the China Records Project collections at the Yale Divinity School Library from a number of standpoints. Their documentation of the work of the conservative American Free Methodist denomination in central China is a useful balance to documentation in other records of more mainline, liberal, and educational work. (Widespread mainline encouragement of medical work in China, for example, is countered by George Schlosser's statement: "The medical work in China, unless it can be a means toward soul saving is in no sense a blessing as I see it, but may even be a curse" Letter to Winifred, 1934 Nov 22) The Schlosser Papers provide useful insight into the dynamics of a missionary family, demonstrating the intimacy and the strains fostered by their chosen lifestyle. The documentation of Mary Schlosser's intensive involvement in evangelistic work provides interesting comparison with other missionary wives who were more exclusively involved with their nuclear family and household responsibilities. Finally, detailed descriptions in the letters and diaries of this manuscript group supplement the body of documentation available at Yale regarding famine relief work, societal routine, and disruption in China during the period 1908 to 1949 and the daily routines of missionary life. Because they did not live on a college campus or in a mission compound, the Schlossers came in closer touch with the common Chinese people than did most Westerners in China. Vivid descriptions of rats, centipedes, and mosquitoes, of idol worship, the night sounds of a Chinese village, dramatic encounters with soldiers, and the suspense of parents separated from their children during a chaotic period of Chinese history enable one to visualize the context in which the Schlossers strove to present the Gospel. ((Letter of Mary to Frances and Winifred, 1934 Mar 4;Letter of George to Mary, 1908 Dec 13.)
Series I is divided into Family Correspondence and General Correspondence. Family Correspondence forms the bulk of the series and consists primarily of letters exchanged between George and Mary Schlosser during the period 1906 to 1912 and letters to and from their children during the period 1929 to 1954. Personal or family news is interspersed with descriptions of events and activities. Interesting documentation of the children's life at boarding school and summer vacations in Chikungshan is available. The family letters are candid regarding discouragements and discomforts suffered by the Schlossers and also give good indication of the strong spiritual basis of their work. The General Correspondence section includes letters to and from the siblings of George and Mary, as well as letters exchanged with colleagues in China and with the Free Methodist Missionary Board. Substantive report letters written by George and Mary for circulation among members of their denomination are in Series III, WRITINGS. Additional correspondence of Frances Schlosser is available in the records of the Yale-China Association held at Sterling Memorial Library.
Series II, DIARIES, consists of seven volumes of the five-year variety, covering the periods 1912-1935 and 1950-1952, and one journal dated 1944. Six of the seven volumes were used primarily by Mary Schlosser. The entries are brief and factual, with little introspection. The diaries provide valuable documentation of the everyday routines of the Schlossers' work, particularly for the 1913 to 1930 period not covered by family correspondence.
The WRITINGS of Series III include report letters and articles written by the Schlossers for publication in denominational periodicals. Two issues of the Praise and Prayer magazine published by the American Free Methodist Mission in China provide an overview of the Mission's work, setting the context for the Schlossers' activities. Minutes of the Free Methodist China Annual Mission Conference for 1934, found in Series IV, supplement the denominational documentation of Series III. Frances Schlosser Scherer's To Be A Pilgrim, 1988, describes her work with Yale-in-China. Also of interest in Series III is an unpublished, undated account by George Schlosser of his conversion experience.
Series IV, PERSONAL ITEMS AND MEMORABILIA, includes biographical information about the Schlossers, five folders of photographs of George and Mary Schlosser, the family, and mission life in China, and other items collected by the Schlossers.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1906-1951, n.d.
II. Diaries, 1912-1952
III. Writings, 1908-1988, n.d.
IV. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1906-1935, n.d.
Disaster relief -- China; Missions -- China; Missions; Social service -- China; Missionaries; Schlosser, George, 1875-1936; Schlosser, Mary, 1885-1955; Free Methodist Church of North America
- Correspondence, 1906-1951, n.d; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The Series is divided into two sections:
  1. Family correspondence is arranged chronologically, with letters to and from George, Mary, and their four children interfiled in one sequence.
  2. General Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by the name of the sender or recipient other than the Schlossers. There are two separate alphabetical sequences in the General Correspondence sections because letters were received after the initial processing had been completed.
  - Family correspondence
    - Family Correspondence, 1906 Nov-Dec (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Family Correspondence, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 2-9)
    - Family Correspondence, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 10-17)
    - Family Correspondence, 1909 (Box 9, Folder 135-142)
    - Family Correspondence, 1910 Jan- May 13 (Box 1, Folder 18-22)
    - Family Correspondence, 1910 May 16- Dec (Box 2, Folder 23-35)
    - Family Correspondence, 1911 Jan, Nov (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Family Correspondence, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 37-38)
    - Family Correspondence, 1929-1930 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Family Correspondence, 1931 May-Sep (Box 9, Folder 143)
    - Family Correspondence, 1931 Oct- Dec (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Family Correspondence, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 41-48)
    - Family Correspondence, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 49-58)
    - Family Correspondence, 1934 Jan- Apr (Box 3, Folder 59-63)
    - Family Correspondence, 1934 May- Dec (Box 4, Folder 64-69)
    - Family Correspondence, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 70-80)
    - Family Correspondence, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 81-84)
    - Family Correspondence, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 85-89)
    - Family Correspondence, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 96-98)
    - Family Correspondence, 1940 Jan- Jul (Box 9, Folder 144-148)
    - Family Correspondence, 1940 Jul- Dec (Box 10, Folder 149-153)
    - Family Correspondence, 1941 (Box 10, Folder 154-160)
    - Family Correspondence, 1942 Feb-Oct (Box 10, Folder 161-163)
    - Family Correspondence, 1942 Feb-Oct (Box 11, Folder 164)
    - Family Correspondence, 1942 Nov-Dec (Box 11, Folder 165-167)
    - Family Correspondence, 1943 (Box 11, Folder 165-167)
    - Family Correspondence, 1944 (Box 11, Folder 168-169)
    - Family Correspondence, 1945-1946 (Box 11, Folder 170)
    - Family Correspondence, 1947 (Box 11, Folder 171)
    - Family Correspondence, 1948-1949 (Box 11, Folder 172)
    - Family Correspondence, 1950-1952 (Box 11, Folder 173)
    - Family Correspondence, 1953 (Box 11, Folder 174-177)
    - Family Correspondence, 1954 Jan-Mar (Box 11, Folder 178-179)
    - Family Correspondence, 1954 Apr-Nov (Box 12, Folder 180-185)
    - Family Correspondence, 1973 (Box 12, Folder 186)
    - Family Correspondence (Box 12, Folder 187-189)
  - General correspondence - 1st sequence
    - Anderson, Palmer, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 99)
    - Chandler, Leticia, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 99)
    - Cook, Mabel, 1928-1934 (Box 6, Folder 99)
    - Easterling, 1932 (Box 6, Folder 100)
    - Edwards, Maud, 1932 (Box 6, Folder 100)
    - Free Methodist Church of North America General Missionary Board, 1906-1935 (Box 6, Folder 101)
    - Gaddis, Myrtle, 1929 (Box 6, Folder 102)
    - Gaudin, Lydia Ogren, 1933,1940,1942,1948,1949 n.d. (Box 6, Folder 102)
    - Green, Lydia, 1935,1954 (Box 6, Folder 102)
    - Jones, Edith, 1911,1933,1938, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 103)
    - Jones, Lora, 1935(?) (Box 6, Folder 103)
    - Kinney, Elva, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 104)
    - Kline, Carrie and George, 1938,n.d. (Box 6, Folder 104)
    - Murray(?), Florence, 1941,1959 (Box 6, Folder 105)
    - Nord, Charles, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 105)
    - Nord, Esther Ogren, 1911,1933,1938,n.d. (Box 6, Folder 105)
    - Nord, Rose Ogren, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 106)
    - Peterson(?), Mattie, 1929 (Box 6, Folder 106)
    - Robinson, M. M., 1906 (Box 6, Folder 106)
    - Sayre, Geneva, 1939,1950 (Box 6, Folder 106)
    - Schaffer, P. D., 1939 (Box 6, Folder 107)
    - Schlosser(?), Martha (sister of George), 1908 (Box 6, Folder 107)
    - Schlosser, John (brother of George), 1912 (Box 6, Folder 107)
    - Silva, E. L., 1934 (Box 6, Folder 108)
    - Smith, Mr. and Mrs. Carroll, 1911 (Box 6, Folder 108)
    - Stoll, Marian and ?, 1919,1932,1933 (Box 6, Folder 108)
    - Wilson, Laura, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 109)
    - Winslow, Carolyn, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 109)
    - Unidentified and first names only, 1934-1954,n.d. (Box 6, Folder 110)
  - General correspondence - 2nd sequence
    - Archer, Bessie, 1955 (Box 12, Folder 190)
    - Ashcraft, E.P., 1941 (Box 12, Folder 190)
    - Backenstoes, 1909 (Box 12, Folder 190)
    - Biblical Seminary in N.Y., 1954 (Box 12, Folder 190)
    - DeWese, Sister, 1929 (Box 12, Folder 191)
    - Gage, Fred, 1965 (Box 12, Folder 191)
    - General Missionary Board, 1947-1951 (Box 12, Folder 191)
    - Greenville College, 1943 (Box 12, Folder 192)
    - Grinnell, Maud, 1953 (Box 12, Folder 192)
    - Grinnell, Mildred, 1941 (Box 12, Folder 192)
    - Kuhn, Dr., 1951 (Box 12, Folder 192)
    - Liaw, Ernst, 1949 (Box 12, Folder 192)
    - Miller, Sister, 1941 (Box 12, Folder 193)
    - Myers, DeWitt E., 1944 (Box 12, Folder 193)
    - Nord, Esther Ogren, 1948,1949,1953 (Box 12, Folder 193)
    - Nord, Rose Ogren, 1941-1954 (Box 13, Folder 194-195)
    - Ogren,? (Mary's mother?), 1915 (Box 13, Folder 196)
    - Reed, Nellie, 1909 (Box 13, Folder 196)
    - Religious News Services, 1950 (Box 13, Folder 196)
    - Schlosser, Katherine, 1941 (Box 13, Folder 196)
    - Schlosser, Ruby Tosh, 1940,1942,1944,1946 (Box 13, Folder 197)
    - Tao Koh, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 198)
    - Veterans Administration, 1944 (Box 13, Folder 198)
    - The White House, 1953 (Box 13, Folder 198)
    - Wiebe, Rachel, 1940 (Box 13, Folder 198)
    - Young People's Missionary Society, 1954 (Box 13, Folder 198)
- Diaries, 1912-1952; Series II
  The diaries are arranged chronologically. One volume belonging to George Schlosser (1924-1928) overlaps with the sequence of volumes kept by Mary Schlosser.
  - Mary Schlosser, 1912-1921 (Box 7, Folder 111)
  - Mary Schlosser and George Schlosser, 1921-1928 (Box 7, Folder 112)
  - Mary Schlosser, 1926-1935 (Box 7, Folder 113)
  - Mary Schlosser, 1944-1952 (Box 7, Folder 114)
- Writings, 1908-1988, n.d.; Series III
  The Series is divided into four sections and arranged chronologically within each:
  Writings of George D. Schlosser
  Writings of Mary Ogren Schlosser
  Writings of Frances Schlosser
  Miscellaneous
  - Writings of George D. Schlosser
    - Circular letter published in The Free Methodist, 1908 Apr 1 (Box 7, Folder 115)
    - Circular letter, 1909 Apr 16 (Box 7, Folder 116)
    - "Exceeding Abundantly Above All We Ask or Think" (Box 7, Folder 117)
    - Account of conversion experience, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 117)
    - Notes, 1944, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 117)
  - Writings of Mary Ogren Schlosser
    - "Kihsien in War Time" - published in Missionary Tidings, 1922 Aug (Box 7, Folder 118)
    - Fragment, c.1920s (Box 7, Folder 118)
    - "Victory in China", 1933 Jun (Box 7, Folder 119)
    - "Grandma Koh", 1934 Jan (Box 7, Folder 119)
    - Circular letters, 1934, 1945-1950 (Box 7, Folder 119)
    - "That Your Joy May Be Full" (Box 7, Folder 119)
    - Notes, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 119)
  - Writings of Frances Schlosser
    - "Be a Missionary Society", 1935 Jan (Box 8, Folder 120)
    - To Be A Pilgrim, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 120)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Articles by Bessie C. Reid and James H. Taylor, 1935 Jun (Box 8, Folder 121)
    - Praise and Prayer, Vol. II, No. 1: including articles by George and Mary Schlosser, 1935 Aug (Box 8, Folder 122)
    - Praise and Prayer, Vol. II, No. 3 (incl. memorial of George Schlosser and article by Frances Schlosser), 1937 Aug (Box 8, Folder 123)
    - Newspaper article on Frances Schlosser, 1948 Mar (Box 8, Folder 124)
    - Missionary Tidings, vol. 59, No. 7 (incl. memorial of Mary Schlosser), 1955 Jul (Box 8, Folder 124)
    - "I Know Who Holds Tomorrow" (memorial of Lora Jean Schlosser), 1966 (Box 8, Folder 124)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1906-1935, n.d.; Series IV
  - Biographical and collected material
    - Biographical information re.George and Mary Schlosser, 1906-1949, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 125)
    - Family notes, memorabilia, 1906,1935,1955,n.d. (Box 8, Folder 126)
    - Miscellaneous poems, quotations, hymns, programs, tracts, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 127)
    - Minutes of China Annual Mission Conference, Sixth Session, 1934 Apr (Box 8, Folder 128)
    - Chinese language material, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 129)
    - List of addresses, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 129)
    - Financial records, 1950-1951 (Box 8, Folder 129)
  - Photographs
    - George D. Schlosser, 1901,1906, 1930,n.d. (Box 8, Folder 130)
    - Mary Ogren Schlosser, 1903,1908, 1930,1941 (Box 8, Folder 130)
    - George and Mary Schlosser, 1911,1935 (Box 8, Folder 131)
    - Family (incl. wedding of James Scherer and Frances Schlosser), 1923-1949 (Box 8, Folder 132)
    - Mission life: Kihsien, 1914,1930 (Box 8, Folder 133)
    - Mission life: Kikungshan, Honan, 1925,1930, 1932, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 133)
    - Mission life: Kiafeng, 1929,1933 (Box 8, Folder 133)
    - Mission life: Chenjchon, Honan, 1933 (Box 8, Folder 133)
    - Mission life: Chungking, 1949 (Box 8, Folder 133)
    - Missions/Traveling in China, 1920, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 134)
    - Photocopied photographs, 1923-1948,n.d. (Box 8, Folder 134)